Broadsides from Mexico Collection, 1676-1927, bulk 1820-1927
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series I: State Broadsides, 1820-1927
  - Zacatecas (2 of 5), January 3, 1851 - December 10, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Subjects referred to are customs, ports, tobacco, Tacubaya, regulation of sulfuric acid, mail rates for newspapers, taxes on the slaughter of cattle, congress, decretos, finances, debt, ships, Spaniards with Mexican citizenship, judges, courts, Roman Catholic Church, manos muertos, army, Texas, fines and fees, prisons, government positions, ayuntamientos, juntas municipales, pensions for veterans wives and children, draft, alliance with Chihuahua and Durango, commission to negotiate the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, identity documents, public education, schools, elections, retired military personnel, marriages, regulation of printing presses, support for the state government of San Luis Potosi battling rebels, cholera epidemic, public health care funding, alcohol taxes, state funeral, judges, constitutional reform, ban on the sale of certain foods, holidays, anticlericalism, subsidies for feeding cavalry horses, war on the frontiers with Indian tribes, salaries for government positions, per diem, travel expenses, prisoners, cartographic and statistical study of the state, expropriation of salt lands and waters, regulations for religious processions, Holy Week, payments by the state to the federal government, Mexican made fabrics exempt from taxes, convicts subcontracted from the state to mine owners to work the mines, state granting a villa the right to hold a ten day fair in late January every year for five years, fees for grazing animals in private fields bordering roads, national guard registration, and counterfeit money.
    Individuals mentioned include Antonio López de Santa Anna, Fernando Franco, Marcos de Esparza, José Mariano de Salas, Casiano Gonzalez Veyna, Manuel Gonzalez Cosio, Antonio Garza, José Joaquín de Herrera, José Gonzalez y Echeverria and Mariano Arista.
  - Zacatecas (3 of 5), January 14, 1854 - December 24, 1856 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Subjects referred to are education, salaries for teachers, assayers, decretos, Indian tribes, bandits, Roman Catholic Church, anticlericalism, elections Isthmus de Tehuantepec, regulations for religious processions, customs, ports, Plan de Guadalajara, thieves to be judged by military courts, cavalry, national guard, government positions, army, observances for Santa Anna's birthday, finances, budgets, taxes, courts, judges, explosives, mines, appropriation of private buildings for military barracks, hospitals, etc., road construction, rebels, commercial licenses for alcohol, tax on mules and burros for road maintenance, valid military decorations, exile of Carbajal, dress code, state seals on diplomas, limit political rights of tenants, affirm private property to salt lands and waters, president of the republic assumption of the states' right to appoint clergy, tithe no longer a civil obligation, mourning for federal minister, tobacco, reestablishment of the Jesuits, military pardon for deserters, pensions, monetary reform, security cards for foreign residents, paper made in Mexico, military draft, regulations defining the nationality of companies with foreign investors, censorship of books including imported books, vagrants, regulations for the border with Texas, federal government assumes the title for tierras baldias, monetary regulations, counterfeit money, mandatory arms in areas with Indian tribes, commercial code, regulations for lighting all public, religious and educational buildings during the evening hours of public celebrations, paint houses one of four approved colors, Plan de Ayutla, prohibition of fireworks, freedom of the press, slaughter of cattle, mail, mandatory public education, soldiers, three months pardon for convicts, and exports of gold and silver.
    Individuals mentioned include José Gonzalez y Echeverria, Mariano Arista, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Ventura Mora, Manuel Gonzalez, Francisco G. Pavón, Manuel Zavala, Fernando A. Velasco, Victoriano Zamora, Juan Alvarez, and Ignacio Comonfort.
  - Zacatecas (4 of 5), January 1, 1857 - May 20, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Subjects referred to are compensation for those lands Santa Anna expropriated, thieves, government positions, reversal of reestablishment of the Jesuits, criminal sentences, negate military honors given by Santa Anna from 1853 to 1855, recognize military honors of those who fought in Guaymas in 1854, finances, budgets, taxes, tobacco, military deserters, permission to marry from bosses or officers necessary for government and military personnel, Plan de Ayutla, courts, judges, bandits, Indian tribes, silver exports, customs, ports, elections, regulations for religious processions, eliminate veterans privileges and salaries, national guard, curfew and martial law, cancellation of railroad contract, pardon for convicts with only two months of their sentences remaining, establishment of a lottery to pay the national debt to New York bankers, salt lands income dedicated to education, closing congress until order reestablished, Constitution of 1857, La Reforma, suspension of privileges granted mining corporations, Roman Catholic Church, anticlericalism, confiscation of convents, nationalization of Church wealth, bandits, exile opposition, disarm public, Independence Day and other public holidays, principle of equality, amnesty for political crimes, decretos, minors under twenty-one need their parents permission to marry, Battle of Azogueros, opposition forces of S. Ramirez, money, sale of Roman Catholic Church property, sanitation, elections, army, frontier ports, secularize hospitals, laws protecting peons, civil marriage, prohibit imprisonment by private individuals of others to gain ransom or personal services, reward for execution of reactionary enemies of La Reforma, freedom of the press, grains, education, 1862 French invasion, draft, and separation of church and state.
    Individuals mentioned include Victoriano Zamora, Ignacio Comonfort, Antonio López de Santa Anna, Juan Zuazua, José María Castro, Jesus Gonzalez Ortega, Manuel Gonzalez Cosio, Benito Juárez, José María Sanchez y Roman, Silverio Ramirez, Miguel Auza and Severo Cosio.
  - Zacatecas (5 of 5), June 2, 1862 - October 1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Subjects referred to are finances, taxes, alcabalas, elections, salary cuts for government employees to fund the war with France, medals for veterans of Aculcingo and Puebla, Mexican silk, courts, judges, decretos, national guard, alcohol, trees, contraband, military deserters, ports, customs, widows must prove the death of their first spouse before remarrying, mines, military discipline for drunkenness, convicts sentenced to Yucatan or Baja California, Roman Catholic Church property, anticlericalism, honors from the state congress, public education of children and adults, coaches, owners of haciendas mandated to allow wood cutting and charcoal making on their lands, draft, weapons, nullify French laws, government confiscation and sale of traitors' property, Cinco de Mayo fiesta, identity documents for foreigners, right to an annual ten day fair in Mazapil, vandalism, bandits, mail, veterans, cavalry, prohibition of meetings of more than five, moving the capital of the federal government to San Luis Potosi, reduction of state functions to defense and security, foreign investment and colonists, pensions, treatment of French prisoners of war to equal treatment of Mexican prisoners of war held by the French, definition of traitors, government positions, resignations from government positions, regulations for grains and seeds, crimes by army personnel, pardon for military convicts, nullify decisions of French courts, slaughter of cattle, surrender of arms for fee paid by government, official mourning, abandonment of the capital by the state government, state of siege, suspension of government functions, release prisoners to the army, annulment of the state of siege, French occupation of the state, fines for using the streets as cloacas or communes, French holiday, sweep streets, French laws and regulations, interim government appointed by Juarez, money, elections, and Plan de Tuxtepec.
    Individuals mentioned include Severo Cosio, Benito Juárez, Ignacio Zaragoza, Ignacio de la Llave, Jesus Gonzalez Ortega, José Maria Saldierna, José M. Avila, Maximiliano, Miguel Auza, Trinidad G. de la Cadena, Genaro Raigosa, and Augustín López de Nava.
- Series II: Federal Government Broadsides, 1676-1910
  - Ministerio de Fomento, Colonización, Industria y Comercio, October 15, 1823 - October 21, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ministerio de Hacienda (Secretaría de Hacienda) (1 of 2), April 22, 1822 - October 28, 1828 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ministerio de Hacienda (Secretaría de Hacienda) (2 of 2), January 28, 1829 - April 3, 1845 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ministerio de Justicia y Negocios Eclesiásticos, June 11, 1822 - July 5, 1835 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Presidente de la República, September 17, 1828 - June 1, 1835 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Primera Secretaría de Estado, Departamento Interior (1 of 2), January 19, 1827 - December 29, 1830 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Primera Secretaría de Estado, Departamento Interior (2 of 2), January 4, 1831 - February 29, 1836 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Primera Secretaría de Estado, Sección de Gobierno, May 24, 1822 - October 9, 1826 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Primera Secretaría de Estado, Miscellaneous Departments, March 1, 1822 - May 31, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Secretaría de Guerra y Marina (1 of 2), March 28, 1822 - September 24, 1828 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Secretaría de Guerra y Marina (2 of 2), January 28, 1829 - July 11, 1856 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Mexico - Miscellaneous Offices, October 2, 1822 - December 12, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Mexico - Miscellaneous Secretarías, August 2, 1824 - January 16, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Mexican Broadsides, 1676 - March 8, 1828 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Seventy-three items are located in Oversize Flat File.